<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.6.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-02-11T14:55:41-06:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">VERITAS LIBERAT</title><subtitle>Truth Frees</subtitle><author><name>VL</name></author><entry><title type="html">Fat</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/health/Fat.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Fat" /><published>2021-02-08T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2021-02-08T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/health/Fat</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/health/Fat.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;nature-makes-good-fat-factories-make-bad-fat&quot;&gt;Nature Makes Good Fat. Factories Make Bad Fat.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You have all heard the dietary advice touted by every major “health” organization that saturated fat and cholesterol cause heart disease, obesity, diabetes, and other modern health epidemics. How do we reconcile this claim with the fact that traditional people eating enormous amounts of animal fat, which contain high levels of saturated fat and cholesterol, were (and in some areas of the world still are) in excellent health? Could it be true that food which has nourished us for many thousands of years, producing a state of almost unbelievable (to modern people) health, could be to blame for the modern health problems?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;lipids&quot;&gt;Lipids&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lipid is the term used to describe both fats (lipids that are solid at room temperature) and oils (lipids that are liquid at room temperature). One commonly discussed, useful method for grouping lipids together is by the “saturation” of Carbon bonds. Lipids are essentially chains of Carbon atoms, plus Oxygen and Hydrogen, bound together by either a double bond or a single bond. Without getting into the specifics, know that double bonds are much weaker and require less energy to break. Single bonds are strong, hearty, and it takes a ton of energy to break them. If a lipid has all of its Carbon atoms bound together with single (strong) bonds, it is said to be “saturated”. If a lipid has all single bonds, but one double (weak) bond, it is said to be “monounsaturated”. If a lipid has more than one double Carbon bond, it is “polyunsaturated”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/Fatty_Acids.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Fatty Acids&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oxidation Reduction reactions were covered in an earlier post, but only in the general sense of transfer of electrons. The transfer of Oxygen or Hydrogen is also considered an oxidative reaction. When Oxygen binds to a molecule, that molecule has been oxidized. These reactions can occur due to contact with another molecule with the right properties or excessive energy, often in the form of heat. Oxidation occurs in a controlled manner for many healthy bodily processes, but when it gets out of control it can cause major problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Free Radicals are reducing agents, meaning they cause oxidative reactions. When left unchecked, free radicals restructure almost every molecule they interact with, turning functioning molecules into dysfunctional or toxic molecules. Even worse, free radicals can turn other healthy molecules into free radicals, causing what is called a Free Radical Cascade. This cascade of oxidative damage destroys healthy tissue, organs, and whole organ systems, leading to disease.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;For the purposes of cooking, we want to pick the kinds of fats that can take heat. On that count, saturated fats (present in butter, coconut oil, lard, and traditional fats) win hands down. Why? Because they can resist a kind of heat-related damage called oxidation. Thanks to their shape, saturated fats have no room for oxygen to squeeze in, and even high heat can’t force these tough molecules to be more accommodating. Monounsaturated fats have room for just one oxygen molecule to sneak in. But it’s not easy, so monounsaturated fat-rich olive oil resists the harmful oxygen-induced molecular rearrangements and is still okay to cook with. Polyunsaturated fat — now that’s another story. Polyunsaturated fat has two places where oxygen can chemically react, which makes oxygen not twice as likely to bind with the fat molecule, but billions of times more likely.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Dr. Catherine Shanahan&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Oxidized Fats are Free Radicals&lt;/strong&gt;. Read that sentence again, &lt;em&gt;and then again&lt;/em&gt;. Burn this concept into your mind, as this reaction is likely the greatest cause of the modern degeneration of health.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;cholesterol&quot;&gt;Cholesterol&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Few natural biological compounds have been both misunderstood by the general population and maligned so viciously by the modern system as cholesterol. Let’s cover the Lipid Cycle now to understand the crucial importance of cholesterol in our body, and how this process can go wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cholesterol is a type of lipid found in the cell membrane of every cell in our body, serves as the basis for the production of sex hormones, becomes activated and turns into Vitamin D in the presence of Ultraviolet light, and is required to produce bile which is crucial for digestion. It is so critical that your liver produces the vast majority of the cholesterol in your body, regardless of your dietary intake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When people talk about “cholesterol levels” though, they are not actually talking about cholesterol. They are talking about &lt;strong&gt;Lipoproteins&lt;/strong&gt;, which are &lt;em&gt;the&lt;/em&gt; essential particle in the &lt;strong&gt;Lipid Cycle&lt;/strong&gt; that transfer lipids throughout the body. They are composed of two parts. The &lt;em&gt;Lipid Core&lt;/em&gt; contains fats, cholesterol, fat soluble vitamins, and various other nutrients. The &lt;em&gt;Apoprotein Coat&lt;/em&gt; is the outer shell which contains many signaling protein molecules that store information such as the lipoprotein’s origin and contents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/Lipoprotein_Types.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Lipoprotein Types&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Lipid Cycle goes something like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Lipids are digested from food or pulled from adipose tissue (fat stored in your body).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;These lipids are packaged into lipoproteins mostly by the intestines and the liver. Here, the lipoproteins are “tagged” with specific proteins that denote the contents of the package, similar to a barcode.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The lipoproteins begin their long journey through the bloodstream.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cells throughout the body that need certain nutrients will “tag” themselves with specific proteins on their surface. This will grab any lipoprotein that floats by and also has a matching tag, indicating it contains the needed nutrient.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The lipoprotein will unload part of its contents into that cell, then continue floating through the blood slightly smaller and more dense. We call these Low Density Lipoproteins (LDL) and they are measured in a standard blood lipid panel.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Eventually, once a lipoprotein has nourished enough cells, it will contain few nutrients and be small and dense. We call these High Density Lipoproteins (HDL) and they are also included in blood panels.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When an HDL molecule passes through the liver, it will be recognized and pulled in for refueling. The core will be filled with fatty nutrients, and the outer layer will be tagged with the correct signaling proteins.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Finally, this lipoprotein will be released into the bloodstream to repair and build the body once again.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This amazing process runs beautifully, as long as these signaling proteins remain intact. If this barcode or label is damaged however, this process is interrupted and becomes very dangerous. A lipoprotein with damaged signaling proteins will get lost, floating aimlessly throughout the body, unable to be recognized by the liver or cells that need them. Eventually the apoprotein shell will fracture, spilling the fatty contents directly into the blood where they will build onto the lining of the arteries. Since these damaged lipoproteins never return to the liver, the natural feedback mechanism to regulate the levels of lipoproteins in the blood is thrown off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The modern system picks up on this disrupted lipid cycle by pointing out the high levels of LDL in the blood. While this is true, high levels of healthy LDL pose no risk. It is these damaged lipoproteins that cause disease. How do these signaling proteins get damaged? Oxidation by Free Radicals!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;vegetable-oil&quot;&gt;Vegetable Oil&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The historically recent rise in arteriosclerosis and heart disease is the result of an historically recent invention of the food industry — refined, bleached, and deodorized vegetable oils…Over the past century, as butter consumption dropped to less than one quarter of what it was, vegetable oil consumption went up five-fold. In 1900, heart disease was rare… Now, at the dawn of the second millennium, heart disease is the number-one cause of death in both men and women. Natural fat consumption: down. Processed fat consumption: up. Heart disease: up— way up. Forget for a moment what the “experts” are saying, and ask yourself what these trends suggest to your inner statistician. The next time you go to the grocery store, see how many foods you can find that don’t contain vegetable oil as an ingredient.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Dr. Catherine Shanahan&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is &lt;strong&gt;Vegetable Oil&lt;/strong&gt; exactly, and why is it not natural? To understand this question, let’s first understand how traditional oils are extracted. There are a handful of traditionally prepared oils from seeds such as flax, rapeseed, and hemp. The extraction of these oils involves a small wedge that can be slowly squeezed tighter and tighter over many hours. The oils from these seeds would then drip out, fresh and full of antioxidants (remember Pillar IV!), and filled with many nutrients. These oils were not used for cooking, because traditional people were aware that heat would destroy these fragile foods. Modern scientific research is proving this ancient wisdom true by revealing that seed oils contain high levels of Polyunsaturated Fats, which we now know are extremely sensitive to oxidation by heat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now let’s cover the modern production process for Vegetable Oils, which contain the contents extracted from corn, canola, soy, sunflower, cottonseed, safflower, rice bran, and grapeseed (often dubbed the “Hateful Eight”). These eight commonly used seeds hang on tightly to their oils, meaning traditional people did not eat these oils because they could not extract them. With modern technology though, machines are able to add inhuman amounts of pressure while heating them, thereby pulling most of their oils out and oxidizing them in the process. The rest of the oil is removed with an industrial solvent, normally hexane (part of gasoline).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/canola_oil.png&quot; alt=&quot;Canola Oil&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The oil at this stage is so physically revolting in both sight and smell that it must go through at least a dozen more stages of processing to convert it into something that has no flavor, and is thus palatable enough to eat. Remember that natural foods which are healthy taste good. No flavor is a warning signal, where our body is telling us something is off about this food!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One other way to denote oxidized fats, which many have heard of, is Trans Fats. Cis Fats are the usual, healthy fats in their natural state that our body is able to recognize and use. Trans Fats are mutated, oxidized, unnatural fats that wreak havoc on our body. All vegetable oils contain trans fats. Even if the label lists a small amount, remember that oxidized fats cause a Free Radical Cascade. This means that trans fats, over time, will turn other healthy fats into mutant fats both in a bottle and in your body. That Canola Oil label says it only has 1% trans fats, but when it’s tested a month later it may be at 5%. Even a small amount of trans fat is enough to cause serious damage, as these vegetable oils do not contain an appreciable amount of antioxidants to slow this chain reaction of oxidation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what fats should you eat? Any fats that our traditional ancestors had access to are always a good choice. Here are the main lipids I make sure to include in my diet:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Animal Fat (Tallow, Lard, Butter, Ghee) from animals raised traditionally: On a large mineral rich pasture in the sun without any additives. This is the best in terms of nutrient density.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Extra Virgin Olive Oil. Just be careful not to heat it too much.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Coconut, Palm, and Avocado Oil&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is more important to remove toxic Industrial Seed Oils, named “Vegetable Oils” (by clever marketing teams trying to trick you into thinking they are equivalent to eating fresh vegetables), from your life than it is to add healthy foods. The integrity of your entire body, especially your brain, depends on the integrity of the fats you put in it. Don’t build yourself with mutant fats. Your health is &lt;strong&gt;far&lt;/strong&gt; too important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope you learned something about fats and make some dietary changes, as Vegetable Oils are definitely not Human Diet approved. There’s nothing better for you than good fats, and there’s nothing worse for you than bad fats. The tricky part is that these fake oils are hidden in almost all processed foods, so your best bet is to prepare your own food from whole ingredients.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re having a hard time believing that your doctor and the health organizations are wrong about fat, I urge you to do your own research on this topic. Here are two studies to get you started: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bmj.com/content/346/bmj.e8707&quot;&gt;Sydney Diet Heart Study&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/27071971/&quot;&gt;Minnesota Coronary Experiment&lt;/a&gt;. Then, look into the financial and personal connections between the food industry, pharmaceutical industry, and the health organizations. Have fun in this rabbit hole.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>VL</name></author><summary type="html">Nature Makes Good Fat. Factories Make Bad Fat.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://0.0.0.0:4000/Lipids.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Milk</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/health/Milk.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Milk" /><published>2021-01-13T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2021-01-13T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/health/Milk</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/health/Milk.html">&lt;p&gt;High quality milk provides all the nutrition required to grow and sustain a mammal. In fact, milk is so important to us mammals that we are taxonomically classified in the animal kingdom based on our ability to produce milk, since only mammals produce milk and all mammals produce milk. Each species produces a slightly different version of milk, with differing levels of enzymes, proteins, fats, and microbes necessary for nourishment. Many traditional cultures value “white blood” for its life sustaining properties and mostly consume it fermented in the form of yoghurt or kefir, which preserves it and allows for much easier digestion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While raw milk is incredibly healthy, the highly processed “milk” sold at grocery stores is not. The factory farmed cows used for mass milk production are trapped in crowded facilities and fed soy and corn, foods they are not able to process in large amounts, putting them in very poor health. They have many critical nutrient deficiencies and do not pass much nutrition into their milk. Traditional people are keenly aware that we should not consume the products of a very sick or unhealthy animal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;pasteurization&quot;&gt;Pasteurization&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pasteurization, the process of heating milk, is another major problem of modern processed milk for several reasons. Naturally, milk includes a whole ecosystem of microorganisms that protect it, making raw milk very resistant to pathogens and an effective probiotic for us. Pasteurization destroys this important microbiome, completely removing its protection mechanism and leaving it wide open for contamination. This is why raw milk sours/ferments, producing a healthy product, but pasteurized milk putrefies, producing a highly toxic product.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This heating process also destroys most of the nutrients. Heat&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;denatures (alters/damages) the structure of amino acids (the building blocks of proteins) making them less bioavailable. It also oxidizes and glycates them, making them inflammatory irritants.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;rancidifies unsaturated fatty acids&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;destroys around 50-80% of water soluble vitamins other than Vitamin B6 and B12 which are totally destroyed&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;reduces bioavailability of all minerals by a factor of about 6&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;destroys 100% of enzymes such as lactase (necessary to digest lactose, milk sugar) and lipase (necessary to digest fatty acids).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, toxic synthetic “vitamins” such as Vitamin D2 or D3 are added.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;homogenization&quot;&gt;Homogenization&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Homogenization is the process of squeezing milk through tiny holes under extreme pressure. This destroys the architecture of the fat globules, disrupting many important signaling molecules on the outer phospholipid membrane. These signaling molecules tell your body important information about the milk and without them, your body often views these zombie fats in processed milk as pathogenic and attacks them. Even without this autoimmune response, which doesn’t always occur, processed milk is exceptionally hard to digest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;plant-milk&quot;&gt;Plant “Milk”&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mass produced plant “milk” is not healthy because the nuts/seeds/grains are not sprouted before processing. Remember the Third Pillar of the Human Diet, which is about Sprouting and Fermenting. Traditional people knew not to eat seeds that haven’t been sprouted or fermented. However, you can sprout nuts or grains and make your own milk alternatives that would likely provide good nutrition (not nearly on the level of raw animal milk, but pretty good).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Soy milk specifically is a disaster. Soy contains scary high levels of many antinutrients such as goitrogens (which interfere with the thyroid), phytoestrogens (which mimic estrogen and throw off the natural balance of the endocrine system), as well as the usual suspects found in seeds which haven’t been sprouted (phytates, oxalates, etc.). This is most tragic when parents, always with good intention, feed soy formula to their growing babies only to cause permanent developmental damage. Traditional Eastern people that ate soy &lt;strong&gt;always&lt;/strong&gt; fermented it for long periods of time to remove these detrimental compounds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Avoid processed “milk” and dairy products. They are fake foods, as are many other modern foods, and are one source of modern degenerative disease. At best, it is a minor net negative in overall health, where the damage it causes can be repaired with an otherwise nutrient dense diet. At worst, it can cause serious, even life threatening issues if consumed regularly in high amounts. Raw cheese is available in many grocery stores, otherwise check out &lt;a href=&quot;http://realmilk.com&quot;&gt;realmilk.com&lt;/a&gt; to learn more and find real milk available for sale near you. I consume a lot of dairy and believe it to be an &lt;strong&gt;excellent&lt;/strong&gt; source of nutrition and good health, but I make sure it’s raw!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>VL</name></author><summary type="html">High quality milk provides all the nutrition required to grow and sustain a mammal. In fact, milk is so important to us mammals that we are taxonomically classified in the animal kingdom based on our ability to produce milk, since only mammals produce milk and all mammals produce milk. Each species produces a slightly different version of milk, with differing levels of enzymes, proteins, fats, and microbes necessary for nourishment. Many traditional cultures value “white blood” for its life sustaining properties and mostly consume it fermented in the form of yoghurt or kefir, which preserves it and allows for much easier digestion.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://0.0.0.0:4000/milking.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Water</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/health/Water.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Water" /><published>2021-01-12T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2021-01-12T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/health/Water</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/health/Water.html">&lt;p&gt;Water is an essential component of life, and drinking clean water is fundamental to health. Tap water contains Fluorine, Chlorine, Pharmaceuticals, Heavy Metals, Plastics, Pesticides, and other harmful compounds which damage our body.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fluorine has a dose dependent relationship with IQ, meaning the more you consume, the less intelligent you will be. This is especially true during critical stages of brain development, but even adults notice a clearing of “brain fog” when they cut out fluoride toothpaste and tap water. Fluorine and Chlorine also compete with Iodine in the body, leading to endocrine problems, most often hypothyroidism. Chlorine also kills micro organisms in your gut which majorly inhibits your immune system, serotonin production, and overall brain function.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pharmaceuticals such as hormonal birth control are estrogens that affect both sexes negatively. Heavy metals accumulate in the body (unless you are following a detoxification plan, more on that later) and cause many toxicity issues that lead to otherwise “unexplainable” health problems. Microplastics are endocrine disruptors as well, leading to thyroid problems and imbalance of sex hormones as they mimic estrogen. Pesticides such as glyphosate and atrazine are powerful endocrine disruptors as well as carcinogens. Atrazine in streams and rivers is actually turning male amphibians into females because it has such a powerful estrogen mimicking effect. The sum of these estrogen mimickers is one reason for the feminization of modern men, where testosterone levels are well below &lt;strong&gt;half&lt;/strong&gt; of what they were just 50 years ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This all sounds horrible, so what can you do? Do &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; drink tap water! Also, the carbon filters found in pitchers and refrigerators do not remove the vast majority of the damaging compounds. Only drink water that has been filtered by either Reverse Osmosis, Distillation, or Spring Water from an uncontaminated source. I installed a Reverse Osmosis filter in my basement and have it feeding my refrigerator so I get clean ice and water. Drink plenty of water each day, but not out of plastic. Instead use glass, stainless steel, ceramic, or any other stable material.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This may seem minor, but start drinking high quality water and I bet you’ll &lt;strong&gt;feel&lt;/strong&gt; the difference.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>VL</name></author><summary type="html">Water is an essential component of life, and drinking clean water is fundamental to health. Tap water contains Fluorine, Chlorine, Pharmaceuticals, Heavy Metals, Plastics, Pesticides, and other harmful compounds which damage our body.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://0.0.0.0:4000/water_blog.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Systems</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/health/Systems.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Systems" /><published>2021-01-11T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2021-01-11T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/health/Systems</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/health/Systems.html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Those who mean to replace natural, traditional foods with modern-day food-like products in the name of health are championing the position that nature doesn’t know best; a corporation does. This is an extraordinary claim requiring extraordinary evidence - a burden they have failed to meet.
Dr. Catherine Shanahan&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The current state of health is abysmal. Look around you as well as within for all the evidence you need. Let’s take a moment to think through this problem from a system engineer’s perspective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You are tasked to determine the root cause of failure for a particular system. It was humming along beautifully for a long time, then major changes were made, and it began failing dramatically. Any competent problem solver or engineer, when given this scenario, would first direct their attention to the “major changes” that the system underwent. It makes very little sense to claim that the conditions of the system while it was working well are to blame for the current problems. But, this is precisely what we have been told about health.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For millennia, humans were in a state of divine union with nature, taking full advantage of its health giving properties. Their skeletons, analyzed today, put ours to shame in terms of development and strength. The few remaining indigenous people still alive today prove, without a doubt, the vitality producing effects of a natural diet. The Agricultural Revolution did have a negative effect on the health of humans, but not enough to put our very existence in danger. At the turn of the 20th Century though, foods began to be invented that drastically altered the course of our health. They are producing an existential problem that must be addressed, especially considering our continually increasing infertility rates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the coming posts, we will examine these “major changes” in detail. Our body is a system which requires certain inputs to operate properly. These processed foods were developed without regard to this fundamental fact. It will become apparent that it’s actually modern foods causing modern health problems, not natural foods.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>VL</name></author><summary type="html">Those who mean to replace natural, traditional foods with modern-day food-like products in the name of health are championing the position that nature doesn’t know best; a corporation does. This is an extraordinary claim requiring extraordinary evidence - a burden they have failed to meet. Dr. Catherine Shanahan</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://0.0.0.0:4000/Systems.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The Human Diet</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/health/The-Human-Diet.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Human Diet" /><published>2020-09-25T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-09-25T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/health/The%20Human%20Diet</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/health/The-Human-Diet.html">&lt;p&gt;Dr. Catherine Shanahan, a biochemist who was inspired by the traditional human population research done by Weston Price, looked at the scientific consensus on the diet of many animals. She noticed that it is easy to learn about what wolves eat in nature, which she would call the “Wolf Diet”, or the Salmon Diet, or the Lion Diet. However, learning about what Humans eat in nature is difficult. The research had not been done, or compiled effectively, and certainly wasn’t common knowledge. The average person today has almost no idea what their ancestors ate just a few hundred years ago, and certainly not before civilization. Disappointed with this severed connection we have with our roots, she set out to determine the &lt;strong&gt;Human Diet&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After extensive Anthropological, Biological, Chemical, and Historical research, she decided that there are “Four Pillars” of the Human Diet. These are four types or groups of foods that all traditional peoples ate, including our ancestors, which give our body the necessary resources to function optimally. None of these pillars can be skipped if excellent health is the goal. She also calls out certain modern foods that absolutely must be avoided in order to follow the Human Diet. A population that follows the Human Diet will achieve good health.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;pillar-i---meat-cooked-on-the-bone&quot;&gt;Pillar I - Meat Cooked on the Bone&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/steak.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Steak&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any food that tastes good, which our hunter gatherer ancestors had access to, is healthy. Through this lens, meat on the bone with skin and fat tastes better because it is more nutritious. Boneless, skinless, lean cuts of meat taste bland because they are largely devoid of the most important nutrients our bodies need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Excerpt from &lt;em&gt;Deep Nutrition&lt;/em&gt; by Dr. Shanahan:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;When cooking meat, the more everything stays together - fat, bone, marrow, skin, and other connective tissue - the better… The better the material you start with, the better it tastes, and the better it is for you. For that reason, and more, animals raised humanely and pastured on mineral-rich soil are best.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;My advice on Pillar 1:&lt;/strong&gt; Regularly eat high quality animal products. High quality means the animal was raised on a pasture (if you’re buying pre-packaged it will say either Grass-Fed or Pasture-Raised), so that it can eat its natural diet, get plenty of sunlight, and move around freely. It also means the animal was not fed GMO crops, given any antibiotics, or highly processed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do not eat factory farmed, grain fed, animals. Not only are these practices horribly inhumane, the products produced by them are not just devoid of most nutrition, they actually contain many toxins. Find local farmers who raise their animals right, and buy directly from them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Try to incorporate more parts of the animal. Opt for the Rib Steak rather than the Ribeye. Go for the 80/20 ground beef rather than the 90/10. Buy bones and make bone broth. Remember, our ancestors ate the entire animal, nose to tail, and our body adapted to need nutrients found only in certain parts of the animal that are missing in the Modern Western Diet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;pillar-ii---organs&quot;&gt;Pillar II - Organs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/liver_onions.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Liver and Onions&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nutrient Density is the amount of nutrition a food provides per gram. One reason we see so much degenerative disease is because the Modern Western Diet is very low in Nutrient Density. The most nutrient dense foods are organs. Gram for gram, there is no food that even comes close, nutritionally, to liver.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Excerpt from &lt;em&gt;Deep Nutrition&lt;/em&gt; by Dr. Shanahan:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The liver is the storage place or the ‘savings bank’ of the body. If there is an excess of protein, sugar, vitamins, and any mineral except calcium and phosphorus, part of the excess is stored in the liver until it is needed….Liver is, therefore, nutritionally the most outstanding meat which can be purchased.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;My advice on Pillar II:&lt;/strong&gt; Eat organs! This is not an optional pillar. At the risk of sounding like a broken record: Remember, our ancestors ate the entire animal, nose to tail, and our body adapted to need nutrients found only in certain parts of the animal that are missing in the Modern Western Diet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider the ancient wisdom: &lt;strong&gt;Like Supports Like&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is good evidence now that eating a specific organ helps that same organ in your body. This makes sense as that organ has all the pre-formed biological components that our body also needs. For example, if you have an under functioning thyroid, there is no better remedy than to the eat the thyroid from a previously healthy animal. I’ve dramatically helped several family members and friends overcome thyroid problems through a few simple steps, one of which is the daily consumption of high quality thyroid and adrenal glands (more to come on this topic).
If you aren’t ready to take the plunge and buy whole organs yet, start with high quality dessicated organ supplements. I’d recommend everyone take a full spectrum organ supplement, especially focused on liver and brain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;pillar-iii---part-1-fermentation&quot;&gt;Pillar III - Part 1: Fermentation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/Saurkraut.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Saurkraut&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fermentation is the amazing process of pre-digestion, preservation, and nutrient enhancement all rolled into one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Excerpt from &lt;em&gt;Deep Nutrition&lt;/em&gt; by Dr. Shanahan:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Bacteria are capable of transforming indigestible, bland, and even toxic compounds into nourishing and delicious foods…Pound for pound, fermented material will have more nutrition packed into it than the raw material it came from because, aside from acting like miniature detoxification machines, microbes add heaps of nutrients to whatever it is they’re growing in…As if it’s not enough that they can free up minerals, preserve our food, manufacture vitamins, and clean up the nasty plant chemicals our bodies can’t handle, once inside your body they will literally fight for your life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When she says fight for your life, she’s referring the powerful effects of probiotics on our gut, and thus immune system. Having a symbiotic, or mutually beneficial, gut biome is crucial to good health and eating fermented food adds tons of helpful organisms to your body. These boost your immunity (the immune system is located nearly entirely in the gut), fight depression (almost all serotonin is made in the gut), keep digestion running smoothly, and produce many other benefits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;My advice on Pillar III - Fermentation:&lt;/strong&gt; Ferment your own foods! Right now I have kombucha, sauerkraut, sourdough, and water kefir fermenting in my house, and plan to start yogurt as well in the near future. I used to have terrible gut problems, as I know many Americans do, but by following the ancient tradition of fermentation, my gut is in far better shape than ever. If you’re not ready to make your own food, then start by buying kombucha, whole milk yogurt with no sweeteners, or sauerkraut and make them part of your daily diet.
This is my favorite topic to talk about because it has such a measurable and noticeable improvement on people’s quality of life. For example, my mom couldn’t handle dairy for decades, but last year she started drinking kombucha and eating yogurt everyday and now she can digest dairy with no issue. Traditional people fermented food for good reason, and you should too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;pillar-iii---part-2-sprouting&quot;&gt;Pillar III - Part 2: Sprouting&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/Sprouted_mung_beans.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Mung Beans&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Animals try to kill you before you eat them. Plants try to kill you after you eat them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many plants, including ones that are considered “healthy” in our modern world, are packed with damaging compounds. People who regularly consume raw seeds - modern grains, legumes, and nuts - often have severely depleted levels of many important minerals such as zinc, as well as a host of gut issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anti-nutrients, one type of damaging plant compound, can even count as negative nutrition. Phytic and Oxalic acid, found in high levels in seeds, actually bind to minerals in your gut, making them unusable by your body!
Lectins, a class of proteins also in seeds, break down the lining of your gut. This then allows anything to leak into your bloodstream, wreaking havoc on your body in many ways, such as causing autoimmune disorders and systemic inflammation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most people notice major health improvements when they cut seeds from their diet entirely, but there is a better way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Excerpt from &lt;em&gt;Deep Nutrition&lt;/em&gt; by Dr. Shanahan:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Seeds are designed to greedily hang on to their stored proteins, fats, and minerals over extended periods of time. To that end, the plant sheaths them in a hard, nearly impenetrable carapace and locks down nutrients with chemical binders that digestive enzymes can’t loosen. Moistening the seeds for a few days activates the plant’s own enzymes-including phytase, which digests phytates-to soften the seed, free up bound nutrients, and even create new ones by converting stored starch and fatty acids into proteins and vitamins.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;My advice on Pillar III - Sprouting:&lt;/strong&gt; Never eat raw seeds. When looking for bread, if the grains were not sprouted before grinding, do not eat them. If beans were not soaked for a few days, do not eat them. If nuts were not germinated, do not eat them.
Almost all modern bread is made from wheat berries which have not been sprouted, and contain far higher levels of Lectins than ancient grains. Look for flours that are heirloom, such as Einkorn or Spelt, and sprouted. Use these to make your own sourdough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Raw seeds do far more harm to your body than you might think. There is not a single known, recorded, group of traditional people who ate seeds without sprouting them first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;pillar-iv---fresh-and-raw&quot;&gt;Pillar IV - Fresh and Raw&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/Yolks.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Egg Yolks&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An oxidation-reduction reaction is where one positively charged molecule steals an electron from another molecule. The molecule that lost an electron is said to have been oxidized. For many bodily processes, oxidation is both necessary and good. But, when there is an over abundance of positively charged molecules, oxidation can get out of hand and destroy healthy biological structures. This is where antioxidants come in. Antioxidants are compounds that inhibit oxidation, and the amount of antioxidants in food begins to decrease once the organisms dies. Fresh, whole foods, including raw animal products, contain a safe and balanced blend of antioxidants because all living organisms use them to prevent damage. (In a later column I’ll talk about the most powerful antioxidant. Hint: It’s not food!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While ‘fresh’ applies to both plant and animal products, ‘raw’ only applies to animal products. Heat destroys nutrients in animal products, making them unusable by our body. In plants though, most nutrients are only bio-available if they are heated (or fermented and sprouted as discussed before). The retinoids (Vitamin A precursors) in carrots, for example, are only about 1% usable when raw, but closer to 30% bio-available when cooked. This is partly because the nutrients in plants are very different than the nutrients in animals, but mostly due to the structure of the plant locking those nutrients in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Excerpt from &lt;em&gt;Deep Nutrition&lt;/em&gt; by Dr. Shanahan:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Locked within cellulose-rich cell walls, vitamins and minerals in high-cellulose plant products pass right through our omnivore’s digestive system. Without heat or caustic chemicals, cellulose can only be broken down using specialized bacteria and extended gut-fermentation - something humans lack the intestinal yardage to accomplish (though they can replicate it via fermentation)…While gaining access to many of the nutrients in plants often requires judicious use of heat, many animal products are so abundant in nutrients that adding thermal energy risks fusing them together. This is why we need to cook our meat so gently, and why raw meat and seafood dishes comprise a valuable part of many international diets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;My advice on Pillar IV:&lt;/strong&gt; Minimize raw plant consumption, because they are the least nutrient dense foods, and maximize raw animal consumption, because they are the most nutrient dense foods in existence. Try to eat fresh (killed the same day) wherever possible. Wild caught Sashimi, pasture raised raw eggs (you probably wouldn’t believe me if I told you how many raw eggs I eat per day), grass fed raw milk, and dehydrated raw organ supplements are all great options.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;review&quot;&gt;Review&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You have health problems. Everyone does today. The first question I would ask you is: Are you eating the Human Diet? Remember what happened to Pottenger’s cats when they didn’t eat the Cat Diet. Their health deteriorated rapidly, leading to infertility and thus the end of the experiment (and the cats). The Standard Western Diet is NOT the Human Diet. In fact it contains none of the four crucial components of the Human Diet. Let’s recap those four pillars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pillar I&lt;/strong&gt; - Meat Cooked on the Bone: Leave the animal as intact as possible. Cook a whole turkey or chicken, a whole leg of lamb, or a steak with the bone attached. Eat all the fat, skin, and connective tissue. Then, use the bones to make bone broth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pillar II&lt;/strong&gt; - Organs: The most nutrient dense foods are organs. Our body evolved eating them and now requires them to operate. High end grocery stores now sell ground meat with organs (like liver and heart) mixed in. Organ supplements are available online as well (&lt;a href=&quot;https://ancestralsupplements.com/&quot;&gt;Ancestral Supplements&lt;/a&gt; and  &lt;a href=&quot;https://organsupplements.com/&quot;&gt;Organ Supplements&lt;/a&gt; are both great).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pillar III&lt;/strong&gt; - Fermentation and Sprouting: Fermented food is incredible for your health, especially gut health. Sprouted seeds are nutritious, where raw seeds are damaging to your body and often count as a net negative in nutrition. If you have gut problems, follow this pillar strictly (avoid unsprouted seeds and load up on fermented foods) and you will notice major improvements!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pillar IV&lt;/strong&gt; - Fresh and Raw: Fresh foods contain the highest levels of antioxidants, which minimize oxidative damage to the body. Raw animal products are the most nutritious versions of animals, and raw plant products are the least nutritious versions of plants. When cooking animal products, the less cooking the better (rare or medium rare at most). Don’t eat a lot of raw plants. Instead eat them cooked, or better yet, fermented and/or sprouted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I urge everyone to make small steps towards the Human Diet. Even a small step will make a difference, and these improvements to your quality of life will motivate you to take more steps in this direction. I also highly recommend reading &lt;a href=&quot;https://drcate.com/deep-nutrition-why-your-genes-need-traditional-food/&quot;&gt;Deep Nutrition by Catherine Shanahan, M.D.&lt;/a&gt; It provides a stellar foundation for understanding how our body works and reacts to food. If there’s one book you read about health, make it this.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>VL</name></author><summary type="html">Dr. Catherine Shanahan, a biochemist who was inspired by the traditional human population research done by Weston Price, looked at the scientific consensus on the diet of many animals. She noticed that it is easy to learn about what wolves eat in nature, which she would call the “Wolf Diet”, or the Salmon Diet, or the Lion Diet. However, learning about what Humans eat in nature is difficult. The research had not been done, or compiled effectively, and certainly wasn’t common knowledge. The average person today has almost no idea what their ancestors ate just a few hundred years ago, and certainly not before civilization. Disappointed with this severed connection we have with our roots, she set out to determine the Human Diet.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://0.0.0.0:4000/eye.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Why Ancestral?</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/health/Why-Ancestral.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why Ancestral?" /><published>2020-07-20T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-07-20T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/health/Why%20Ancestral</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/health/Why-Ancestral.html">&lt;p&gt;Why am I looking to our ancestors and nature for guidance?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;weston-price&quot;&gt;Weston Price&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/harvesting_fish.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Man Holding Fish&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Weston Price, head of the American Dental Association, traveled the world in the 1930’s to gather data on traditional indigenous peoples. He wondered why the majority of people in the United States have cavities and crowded teeth. He discovered, much to his shock, that these traditional populations, when eating their traditional diets, had nearly zero cavities and fully developed jaws and skulls, meaning they had no crowding of their teeth. When these same populations established contact with civilization and began eating modern foods, their health deteriorated considerably, giving them cavities and poor development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What were these people eating, and avoiding, to put them in a state of such excellent health?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;pottengers-cats&quot;&gt;Pottenger’s Cats&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/black_cat.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Black Cat&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Francis Pottenger also performed nutrition research in the 1930’s. His experiments involved feeding groups of cats either raw animal products (meat, organs, bones, milk) or cooked animal products. After 10 years, several generations on the raw food diet were in excellent health by every measurable marker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cats fed the cooked food diet did not fare so well. By the end of the first generation, they already began developing degenerative disease and lacked energy. The second generation had poorly developed skeletons, especially in the skull, and more degenerative disease. The third generation had significantly degenerated to the point that very few were fertile, and none of the much smaller (in size, mass, and population) fourth generation lived past 6 months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The good news is that this degeneration is reversible. Cats in the third generation cooked food group were switched over to a raw food diet and became more healthy quite quickly. They then produced a new generation which was properly developed and had far less degenerative disease.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This study shows that simply eating the “wrong” foods for our body is enough to produce terrible results. Cooked animal products are not nutritious enough to supply cats with all they need to properly develop, but raw animal products are. What are the “right” and “wrong” foods for humans?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;compare&quot;&gt;Compare&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider the state of our health in the modern United States:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;At least half of adults have prediabetes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Almost 40% will get cancer in their lifetime.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;650,000 people die every year from heart disease.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Half of people are obese.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The average person needs several cups of coffee just to make it through the day.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Depression and anxiety are “normal” now.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contrast that with, for example, the health of the Innuit or Eskimo peoples on their native diet of almost exclusively whole seafood (whale, fish, seal) and whole caribou. They have perfectly formed skeletons, perfect teeth, and more than twice the thickness of the skull as us. They aren’t plagued by modern degenerative diseases, such as those listed above, and have incredibly good blood panels. Hearty, strong, full of energy, happy. These are all words regularly used to describe these people.
Note: Learn more about these impressive people by reading &lt;em&gt;The Fat of the Land&lt;/em&gt; by Vilhjalmur Stefansson.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Something is clearly wrong with our way of life. We are paying the price for abandoning our nature. The modern person is only a shell, not coming close to their potential. For this reason, and many more, we must study the wisdom of traditional knowledge, proven successful for thousands of years, to teach us how to live.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the posts that follow, we’ll elaborate more on the differences between a traditional healthy diet and the modern toxic diet. Diet is the first area of health covered because I believe it’s the most important.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>VL</name></author><summary type="html">Why am I looking to our ancestors and nature for guidance?</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://0.0.0.0:4000/nature-2.jpg" /></entry></feed>